okay
hopefully
this uh works if not we'll restart
but uh let me know in the chat
how the video quality is because i'm
getting
multiple
different uh messages from it but um
error
hopefully not error
see here
there we go
if it's glitching
please tell me
we'll restart but um
should smooth out
we'll see
but uh today we have actually an
incredible stream um and i that's why i
really hope that we're we have good uh
quality
um
video because
this one is very unexpected um it was uh
it's going to be about carl kristen
latest discussion with kerchai mungle
and
that
discussion
um
was
i don't know it was it was unexpectedly
profound really was and um
okay now we're seeing excellent
connection so hopefully we maintain that
uh but hit the like button and uh
please uh share with anybody who you
find this valuable with
um
let me see here real quick just checking
something
just monitoring
video quality so
okay
um
so carl fristen was recently on
kurt jay mungle's um
stream and
uh he and came up with a
theory i guess you could call it called
the free energy principle and uh we're
gonna discuss it but
first just some housekeeping
uh we will not be having a stream this
third a a call this thursday i'm going
out with my wife um
uh to go see a show
which is not something that we've done
in a very long time but uh
we are gonna at least try and do that
we'll see if
our coveted test comes back positive or
negative should come back negative but
we'll see hopefully uh stating that word
does not
you know mess with the stream too much
but
um
that uh so we won't have a stream on
thursday
or a call on thursday but we do have a
stream this week as obviously right now
i'm not sure if we're going to do some
type of thing making up this the call on
tuesday
if we do it might be on sunday but
to be honest probably not um it's just a
crazy month and
you know we've had
some family emergencies this month uh
my uh
my father-in-law passed away last week
that was uh
very unfortunate um
and
just a number of other things that
eventually i will discuss
but uh not quite yet
and uh
we're getting back in the swing of
things though
so i appreciate everybody's patience
so the free energy principle
guys this
blew my mind because i will say that
carl pristin's work appears to be the
closest to mine that i've ever seen and
that is really saying something in an in
a landscape where
there's a lot of theories
quote unquote theories of everything
that
are
uh very similar even if they you know
their creators won't admit it or they
won't if if it's not so obvious um you
know on the surface but they are
actually getting
to be quite similar that doesn't mean
that they are redundant either they're
not necessarily redundant
they each have a you know they're on
specific
um
strength i guess so you would use them
for different things
but here
the free energy principle
the free energy principle is a formal
statement that explains how non-living
and living systems remain in
non-equilibrium steady states by
restricting themselves to a limited
number of states
it establishes that systems minimize a
free energy function of their internal
states not to be confused with
thermodynamic free energy which entails
beliefs about hidden states in their
environment the implicit minimalist
minimum
minimalization
minimize minimization wow minimization
that's not a word you hear every day of
free energy is formally related to
variational
bayesian methods and
was originally introduced by carl
fristen as an explanation
uh for embodied perception in
neuroscience which is also known as
active
inference okay
uh the free energy principle describes
the behavior of a given system by
modeling it through markov blanket which
minimize tries to minimize the
difference between their model of the
world and their sense and association
perceptions basically of the world the
difference can be is described as a
surprise and is minimized by continuous
uh correction of the
world model of the system okay basically
so it's talking about how your
perception of the world
and the model of the world that you have
in that uh helps you orient basically
like what what you think about the world
is continuously corrected given new
information from the external world in
an ideal you know model
and that this helps you minimize
things that are unexpected okay so like
surprise
and um
kristin believes his principle applies
to mental disorders as well as
artificial intelligence ai
implementations based on the active
inter inference principle have shown
advantages over other methods
this is probably
why
our
models are similar is because
the original
goal of my work was not to do anything
related to physics or metaphysics or
mathematics it was to
try and figure out what would be
necessary for
the creation of a
self-aware technological being so uh
artificial general intelligence
essentially and
um even though i don't like that term
and
basically that would include what is
technologically necessary and also
what is um
informationally necessary therefore and
then also
what
that led to you know an investigation of
what is the self what is consciousness
who how do you i know what i am how do i
make sense of my world
exactly basically what the free energy
principle and markov blankets seem to be
uh
you know associated with
so a markov blanket
is
the main
model of this of this theory essentially
and
in statistics and machine learning when
one wants to infer a random variable
with a
set of variables usually a subset is
enough and other variables are useless
subsets containing useful information
it's called markov blanket
okay well we'll look more into this in a
bit but
um
carl fristen
creator of the free energy principle
it's a british neuroscientist at
university college london and an
authority on brain imaging he uh gained
a reputation as the main proponent of
the free energy principle active
inference
and predictive coding theory
fristen studied neuroscience
physics and psychology at
the university of cambridge in 1980 and
completed his medical studies at king's
college hospital in london
okay
so
this is
the
right here this is uh
the stream that we're going to be
discussing today
right here don't be diluted by gurus or
yourself carl kristen on the perils of
investigating consciousness
uh dear realization and the free energy
principle
so
thank you
i was listening to this earlier again
at 1.5 speed okay let's go to normal
and
let's go to
get started first clip
and i will show you why
this um
this work of his is so close to sentient
singularity theory i mean let's just do
that first so
sentient singularity theory
right here
says that a sentient singularity
observes four primary perspectives which
are inside outside separate and oneness
these four perspectives are
interdependent and entangled as the
awareness of one of them entails the
awareness of all four
because if you are aware of what is
outside you you are aware of what would
be inside you you are aware of what is
separate from you then you are also
therefore aware of what would be one
with you because you can't be aware of
what is separate from you without being
aware of what would be you know one with
you
you know there it's they're
interdependent
and
in objectivity
there is no next to there's no above
there's no next to there's no to the
right of to the left of below
there's only
uh and because there's not there is only
somethingness
when you're thinking about like hellonic
nested structures which is what sentient
singularity theory describes like
uh
emergence as kind of
there is no cr you can't cre if you are
all there is if you as a sentient being
are all there is there's nothing else
then you can't create something that's
next to you you can only create
something that's inside of you because
there is no
world outside of you
to create another thing in you are the
world
it's like you are the dweller and the
dwelling and in order to create another
dweller you have to create it within you
so
because of this
the way in which you escape relativity
but
but allow for you know multiplicity
still
of states and and beings is
you uh
the relationships are based on what is
inside and what is outside so
i am
outside of you
and my cells are inside of me
you know fetus is inside of a mother
etc but once it's born it's outside of
the mother so this is
how you can orient yourself within a
lineage chain
or
a
structure composed of multiplicity of
sentient singularities or sentient
beings and so
you can orient and uh and yourself and
um and describe relationships
without having relativistic
metrics and definitions and and
perspectives
like you know
i don't know feet and miles per hour
and uh
pounds or
also you know
faster bigger smaller
above below
but you can do inside and outside
because these are objective
relationships they're
not
um
they're
they're not dependent upon size
or
uh space even because you don't need
space in order to have
in the traditional sense in order to
think about whether or not something is
inside something else
even though that kind of seems
untrue that's
we're not thinking about space and any
kind of measurable sense still it's not
like
um length with height you don't need
this
facial
structuring
um and you don't need
uh
you know speed or feet or anything like
that
so
these four primary perspectives
of inside outside separate and oneness
are what allowed me to
move forward with this work and
go and do things that
were i didn't expect to be able to do
which is to describe reality essentially
uh
outside of relativity but
still
um not
still within multiplicity so not within
oneness you can either say everything's
one or you could say
everything is relativistic and you know
have
all the ways in which we currently
describe our universe but
um
but in order to be in that space in
between those two
where
there's multiplicity in some
fashion
but no more relativity you have to have
uh these four primary perspectives
and
i've seen other
philosophers
do
some things that were similar since then
these were independently
deduced by me
all of this was i avoided other people's
work until i was pretty much finished
and then
i saw that eric weinstein's theory
geometric unity starts with x4 this is
the same thing
clearwind's theory of emergence theory
starts with the tetrahedron this is also
the same thing i'm pretty sure the
constructor theory also has a four
dimensional structure that is at the
heart of it in some form or fashion
same thing
and
the free energy principle does as well
and so
we are going to look at that
so
also sentient singularity theory
says that
uh
that a sentient singularity is a
sentient being okay
and it's basically
you could it says here um a sentient
singularity theory denotes a singularity
as the structure that has the property
of infinite oneness such as a mobius
strip strip and
one being that is composed of many or
one being that is composed of many
beings such as a multicellular organism
or a
cell that is composed of molecules or a
molecule that is composed of atoms etc
and um that these are the building
blocks of the cosmos the sentient beings
what i call sentient singularities
and
each one has these four primary
perspectives that it perceives
so
this is
we're going to start getting into what
uh
the free energy energy principle is this
the first clip
the most likely paths that the system
will take particularly the states of the
particle or person that we're talking
about
we can associate those paths at least
action with paths that minimize
something called variational free energy
most
likely
take particularly the states of the
particle or person that we're talking
about
notice that he said particle or person
okay so they are they have the same
intrinsic
uh
fun functionality i guess in in
his model
we can associate those paths at least
action with paths that minimize
something called variation free energy
so that's basically it and then the
story as well what's what's variation
free energy well variation free energy
is as with all actions in physics it's
just a
a path integral or a time interval
a sum an accumulation of a functional
usually known as a lagrangian
where in this instance the from the
functional in question this variation of
free energy
can be read as exactly the same quantity
that statisticians
um
psychologists
people trying to understand data
would treat as
a proxy for
the evidence for some model of the world
so this is known as bayesian model
evidence um
statistically it's also known as a
marginal likelihood the likelihood of
these
sensory data the sensory the paths
through the sensory states
under a particular model
that would try to explain
a hypothesis that will try to explain
those data
so
you've got this interpretation or
certainly the fact that the functional
form
of this variation free energy that is
being minimized by the paths of least
action of the autonomous the active and
the internal states on something a
particle or a person
now looks as if it is trying to minimize
the quantity which provides an
approximation or a
approximation
to
marginal likelihood or moral evidencing
so in other words it looks as if the
most likely paths are trying to maximize
model evidence
so
one can read that in many different ways
one can read that um and um as jakob
howie has read it
a philosopher a neuroscientist who um
has
a commitment to understanding to this
kind of formulation as self evidencing
literally
interacting with your
environment
actively inferring engaging with your
experienced world your eco niche
in a way that looks as if you're trying
to solicit
the most evidence
for your model of that world
this quantity
okay
okay so
basically it is
he's talking about sentient beings he's
talking about
how you
go and you look at the world and you're
looking for evidence that is confirming
of the of your current model of
or or construction or vision
of what the world is and we're going to
get to how this can be actually
exploited
and how this can be dangerous later
because they talk about it um but there
is actually
this can be dangerous the exploration of
consciousness can be
quite dangerous but not even the
exploration of consciousness you can be
your consciousness can be manipulated
and you don't
and
it's important to be able to identify
where that would be
get some water okay
so
this is the free energy
principle
but the special thing about the free
energy principle
is it tries to understand the
relationship of something
in relation to everything else
so you're starting from the premise that
something exists and then you have to
think carefully
well what is a thing and how do i
distinguish it from something else so
immediately you start you have to
introduce a partition
between the states of things
that comprise states that are internal
to the thing and states that are outside
the thing and
thereby in i'll think carefully about
how those states are coupled and what
happens is that you have to introduce a
further set of states known as blanket
states
that constitute a markov blanket that uh
mediate a bidirectional exchange between
the internal states and the external
states so you've got this
notion now of taking the states of any
universe
any system that you want to try and
understand
and partitioning it or carving it into
four subsets internal external and then
sensory active states that constitute
the blanket states where the active
states mediate the effects of the
internal on the external
the inside on the outside
and the sensory states conversely
mediate the influences of the external
on the internal so with this particular
partition which you wouldn't need if you
wanted to now just move on and develop
um
say quantum mechanics or statistical
mechanics or around your classical
mechanics okay so a few things here
one
now
i hope some of you at least watching
this see
why this is so amazing because
his four-part partition
fro
uh with markov blankets as he calls them
which is basically what i think
is what i would call a sentient
singularity but he calls
he calls uh them sentient artifacts so
later on in this he says these four part
per this four-part partition is
necessary to begin the formation of
uh sentient artifacts which is exactly
what i'm talking about is this four
uh
these four primary perspectives are
necessary for
any sentient singularity and uh to be
able to perceive itself as
as uh
and achieve self-awareness so and also
therefore awareness of what is not self
because you must be aware of self in
order to be aware of what is not self
and you must be aware of what is not
self in order to be aware of what itself
so they're
interdependent and um
and this is different than just simple
neural nets that we currently have in a
ai which isn't really ai
there's no such thing as ai
not even agi is ai there's just
intelligence and it's not artificial
it's just natural it is it's like uh
it's like consciousness it's everywhere
and
but what he's saying here is exactly
what
sentient singularity theory is about it
is about how do you distinguish
between different things
but outside of relativity okay that was
my
kind of
it was the end result of my work but it
wasn't actually
the original goal
and
uh
understanding sentience was the original
goal or consciousness
of self-awareness i guess you could say
is better putting it that was the
original way that i thought about it
when i was first formulating this but
uh and in
uh sentient singularity theory
you have inside outside which uh and
separate and oneness so in
uh free energy principle
and mark off blankets you have
um
you have internal external so inside and
outside and you have
active and sensory
states i guess so
um
one of them would be your
it would be
you are
the mechanism the process that you're
that is your that is happening is you
are
receiving
um or absorbing
sensory information so information is uh
from the outside is moving to the inside
so it's
um
it is uh
you're you're
receiving input that's what i'm trying
to say you're receiving input
and
then
the
uh active state is when you are now
taking that information that you
sensed
uh through your sensory mechanisms
and you have processed it and you are
now acting in accordance with that new
information that you have uh
in the that new information that has
been input into your system and so
that is active
state and what it is is it's just you
acting
on the outside world
and uh it is your output so the sensory
you sensing things is your input is your
receiving input
and you
um acting is you are producing output
okay so that output will then be the
input for the other observers that are
able to perceive whatever that output is
in the world that you are putting out
and um
that would be impacting other sentient
beings or sentient artifacts or sentient
singularities as i would call them
sentient singularities as um
as
uh fristen would call them sentient
artifacts so
this is exactly the same
and
uh
i what he says is that
and we'll get into it in a minute but
the way in which he models
uh
how
what what part of this four-part
partition can impact the other parts is
fascinating and i'm going to look more
into it how it relates to mine because
uh
maybe not on this stream but
in
sentient singularity theory
and i'm not sure if this is the most
up-to-date model but
you have like oneness
outside inside and separate and they are
defined by each other so separate is
inside or outside of oneness
and
inside would be separate and oneness
outside is separate from oneness
and oneness is outside and inside of
separateness kind of so
um
it's
and not and i'm not exactly sure if
that's the best definition like i said i
don't think this is the most updated
model but these two are definitely
correct and this one is at least closed
so separate
usually would mean
um
uh
it could be outside of oneness and it
could be
inside of oneness but it's depending on
your perspective so you separate from
another is
uh inside of
oneness
and you
observing something outside of you
uh
as separate from you
that would be outside of oneness but you
observing yourself
inside of you as separate from another
that is outside of you with the inside
of oneness so
it's kind of complicated but it's
uh these two are definitely much easier
this outside and inside but
it
he has um
sensing and acting and i have separate
and oneness and um
so active would be oneness in my
is
in alignment with oneness in my model
and
sensing is separateness because you
sense that which is separate
and then you act and
uh once you act on a system you become
part of the system so you become one
with the system but as you sense the
system
uh you're not inherently one with it
even though people who are into quantum
mechanics are like that's not true but
um
what
kristen said though at the end of the
clip that i played is that
this is basically that you cannot use
this to get to quantum mechanics
and i totally disagree with that there's
a reason why there's four fundamental
forces
okay
and
that they are really
the strong force the weak force and
electromagnetism and the strong force
and uh and electromagnetism are on two
sides reflecting across
uh the weak force and then they're kind
of summing to
oneness which would be gravity and
we don't really fully understand this
relationship yet um and that's the point
of trying you know all these theories
that have the goal of unification with
gravity they've already unified the
other two forces
the other forces but they have not yet
unified uh them with gravity
and there's a reason for that but
this
um
you can get
quantum mechanics and the standard model
from
these four primary perspectives it's
there's more you have to get more
um
than just these at least i think than uh
these four primary perspectives
um
in order to get to the standard model
but
it's so close and you could use the free
energy principles models as well as
active and sensing and
uh
internal and external you can do it but
uh i mean if you can get to the four
fundamental forces these forces
correspond to
force carrier particles and these force
carrier particles are part of the
standard model and
you know
that
when you understand what is
what is an electron
and what is
um
a boson and what is a new neutrino
at least what i think they are you
they stem from
those particles
stem from
relationships that are described by
these this four-part partition so
uh they're described by interaction
between
internal and external
scented artifacts
and um
and
that
is basically that does mean that you can
get quantum mechanics from
uh
the free energy principle essentially
which is amazing
but um i'm not claiming to do a great
job explaining that right now but it's
going to be in the paper that i'm uh
going to be releasing kind
at least
at least the correspondences will be
there
so like i said please hit the like
button uh if you're watching this you
find this interesting uh share this
comment any questions in the chat that
you may have and i will get to them um
but
this his work fristen's work is
incredible there was a four stream that
he did with kurt and i have not uh
finished watching that yet i will finish
watching that and if it's if i feel it's
worth
you know doing an episode on
even though i've already done this one
uh then we'll do it but i i thought that
the two-hour one that they did which is
their most recent one highly suggest
watching that one even kurt said to
watch that one first before the other
um
and
i think that's probably true because
this
it's tough to it's tough to understand
even uh one of the things that came up
in the stream is that
uh
there was a word that was actually used
free energy print kurt said that many
people describe the free energy
principle as inscrutable i've never
heard this word before but it means like
unable to unders be understood
and
yeah
we'll we'll look at it but i i have a
different reason for why it seems
inscrutable to some people and intuitive
to others which is what it really is
than what briston
said but
there you go
energy so what that means is that
if you now understand um or have at hand
the functional form
of your variation free energy
that depends upon
posterior beliefs or beliefs about the
outside world
under a generative model quite simply a
probability density over
the external causes of the
consequences that are the sensory states
and then you can use that methodology
use that principle to start to simulate
to build sentient artifacts that behave
in the way that we assume under the free
energy principle that you and i are
behaving let's see if i can make a
nutshell of the nutshell for some people
who are more familiar with physics so
let's say you have a ball you want to
know the dynamics of the ball you can
understand this with newtonian force and
that's useful for certain calculations
or you can think of it as minimizing a
lagrangian and then that actually
provides a more useful for most cases
way of calculating the trajectory of the
ball so then
right there when i said ball we've
identified the ball now here you're not
just limiting yourself to balls you're
saying let's say cells instead of
talking about people because we can
break it down simply at least for me for
myself i find it much more easy to think
of a cell okay so then we want to know
what are the dynamics of the cell how is
the cell a single cell going to act
okay firstly the first step would be
identifying that cell
and when you mention the word markov
blanket that's a way of identifying what
this object is because in order to
identify what an object is it's often
useful to identify what it isn't at the
same time what it is and isn't so that
markov blanket delimits the cell now is
that correct so far absolutely yeah so
you're having the cell is a perfect
example here you've got your
a cell is just defined by the boundary
which would be the surface of the cell
and that would essentially be the
sensory states that i was talking about
before
the inside the intracellular states
would be the internal states and then
the milieu in which that cell lives
which is usually in a bunch of family of
other cells
will constitute all the external states
so
you've made the very first step just
talking about a cell a thing
you define it in terms of this partition
into internal external and the uh the
sensory states that bound and separate
the inside from the outside you may be
asking well where the active states come
for a cell i usually like to associate
those with something called actin
filaments that just lie underneath the
surface the sensory states and
actively push the cell surface say oh
the philia and the the um
the mechanisms that cause motion of the
cell should it move around
so
those parts those states that are
responsible for cellular motility so
we're now thinking about a moving cell
swimming cell for example
that you need to supplement that
partition with with active states so
that's absolutely the first step um and
then you're going to go on and now
translate the ball what's the ball
in this in this metaphor
you also mentioned the word
bi-directional earlier and when i was
learning about this the way that i like
to understand this was that in computer
science generally computer scientists
think and can only think in terms of you
have an input and then there's a black
box and you have an output and that's
essentially computer science that's
exactly what i said okay so
you
have a cell you have a or an organism
you have a
molecule an atom
uh
you know whatever it may be even a cast
or a technological sentence
and um
it
is it interprets its world and you
interpret it as
uh as its own hollandic entity hollandic
a whole on is like a structure that is
self
referencing so kind of in a way so here
hold on
define it
a hole on
oh look this is fascinating
a hole on is something that is
simultaneously whole
in it of itself as well as part of a
larger hole in other words hole ones can
be understood to constitute constituent
parts
um
of a
holes of a hierarchy this is exactly
what i talk about all the time
how hierarchy is necessary to understand
all of this because hierarchical
structures is how you
deduce what is
what structures are sentient artifacts
and which structures are not because the
hierarchical
lineage that you go through which is
like
a cell is inside of an organism an
organism is inside of a cast a cast is
inside of a
of a
of a nation but really that means like a
technological
sentience or technological singularity
it's inside of technology
and uh molecules inside of a cell and uh
an atom is inside of a molecule so
this is how you know
which direction
uh
to
look in and
in which these
sentient artifacts
manifest and and uh evolve but
otherwise you start thinking about stars
and you start thinking about planets and
you're like this planet sentient is star
sentient is a black hole sentient
and uh you know is a galaxy a sentience
and you start branching off into the
wrong direction and you're like well you
know a person is inside of a planet and
a planet is inside of a
solar system and a solar system is a
star basically and then an ad is inside
of like a galaxy and the galaxy's inside
the universe and
you've branched off in actually the
wrong way and you don't act you cannot
get to where you
need to get to uh but it's close but
it's not quite there but
uh
but
this is just very important exactly what
they said is that uh you know knowing
what is outside you
and knowing what is inside you are two
parts of two sides of the same coin you
get that coin at the same time you can't
get
an understanding of that which is
outside of you but not yet understand
what is
inside of you or really you cannot get
an understanding of that which is
separate from you
but not uh
but have an understanding of what is one
with you what who are you
so in order to know you you have to know
uh what is not you and so this is
exactly what they're talking about this
is what the free energy principle is
about and it is basically saying that
this this exchange of inputs and outputs
of information so basically your acting
states are your
uh output and your sensory state is when
you are receiving input
um
this
like
uh you know mobius strip never ending
mobius strip of information where it's
basically you receive information and
then it's flipped and and uh and
processed and then spit back out as an
output which is an action so you sense
as an input and then it
goes you know it is processed by your
mind organized into a hierarchy
differentiated you know whatever
and then orient it around a goal and
then spit back out in terms of uh
action and
this is
uh you
um becoming one with any structure
because
anytime you
act on uh on a system you become one
with that system and
um any time that you sense that system
you are sense you are perceiving
yourself as a separate from the system
because you were perceiving the system
separate from you so it's that
separateness from sentient singularity
theory is the
sensory state from
uh
is the is the perception it is the
the
uh
it is the perspective that is perceived
during the sensory
um
uh
aspect or part of this four-part
partition
and then
the oneness is perceived is the
perception when you are acting so you
are becoming one with the system because
you have acted on it and um
you perceive yourself as separate from
it when you're perceiving it initially
so
these are the perspectives that are
associated with
um these four park park this four-part
partition
and um
here we can just look at this real quick
um so we can go to my work
we can go to
right here
okay
right here there we go just wondering
where it went
okay so basically this right here this
is a markov blanket
okay
so
you have
intrinsic processes and extrinsic
processes
and
uh and i'm not saying this perfectly
correct but uh this
i've been working on i don't want for a
while so there's definitely some stuff
going on here but i have made
corrections and i'm not sure if this is
the best uh model yet but you have
intrinsic processes and you have your
extrinsic processes and it's basically
this like mobius strip of information
processing and this is a sentient
artifact or sentient singularity and
uh
you've got you know perception
and
interpretation prioritization
differentiation this is kind of all
internal
this is your external
um which is
uh you know
i have consideration here but it's an
action uh proclamation
and um
you know there's a few others but
we've done some work since then i'm not
going to get into that
but
let's let this load for a second because
it's such there's so much here
come on
sentient
the energy
okay so you've got sentient singularity
theory here
free energy principle here
and
then you have oneness separate
outside and inside so let's just make
this easier inside
outside
so
all right
oneness
and then here in the free energy
principle markov blanket
you have
internal
external
you have a separate which is sensing
and
or sensory
and active
uh
action
as sensing
sensory
sensing
okay essentially
okay
so there you go
these are the same thing obviously
but
there's a bit of a difference because
what is happening is
this is very much about perspectives
and this is about
kind of uh
functions
this would be
this would be your um
um
constraints and degrees of freedom would
be
kind of like
almost like this kind of
not saying that this is exactly correct
but i'm just kind of riffing on it a bit
just to think
okay so
huh
constraints are limits kind of you know
but there you go
this is the same thing
you have geometric unity's x4
and uh
and you've got the tetra you drawn from
clearwinds theory and i'm sure there's
more but i mean you can
i'm not saying these align because they
don't because i moved things around but
it's really going to be um
this would be gravity
and then
outside would be
separate and then this will be
and i think
strong
worse
nuclear force
there you go
i don't know if that's correct or not
but
it's fine
all right
but this
is about
function it's about uh
it's about what you're doing
okay so like
what
um
is
happening
what
is
perceived
so my theory is about what is perceived
free energy principles about what is
what is happening
okay
and
i don't want to
say on this stream which one is more
fundamental even though i'm pretty sure
it's going to be
sentient singularity theory just because
the free energy principle is about
minimizing deviations from the
you know truth
uh in your model i guess um of reality
so
and it's about what is happening
within this
the various um
parts of you i guess of a sentient
artifact
and then a sentient artifact is a
sentient artifact by definition because
it is perceiving it is feeling which is
perception it um
and
what you perceive
is what dictates your constraints and
degrees of freedom so your pers the
perspectives that you have
are what
are responsible for what you your
allowances
okay
you can't see then you are limited in
what uh your actions can be and also in
what your
uh
your sensing is so
but if you can see then it opens up
sensory
state kind of and then it also opens up
an action state for you and
this is
much more about what is being perceived
not yet what is what is being done
okay so what is
i guess you could say what is being done
so it's almost like
this is step one
this is step two
as we start to like
uh i guess make changes
to the world
and then you get to
you know
uh probably geometric unity
and
then you get to
maybe emergence theory because all of a
sudden now we're in it
where we're talking about
three-dimensional space
uh where we've moved back into
relativity almost because you were
talking about the pixelization and
or the
the fundamental pixels of a
three-dimensional
uh space would be tetrahedrons according
to
emergence theory so
but this is
way before you get to a
three-dimensional space
but
like i said they all have their unique
um
like strengths and purposes
fascinating doesn't it
okay
here this is good so next clip
there is a thing that's in play there's
a mark of blankets so what that tells
you is
in principle it was possible to take
all the states that constitute say any
niche
and this um find identify
the thing of interest saying now say me
and my internal states and so and then i
would um identify my blanket states and
then i got the rest of the states but
now i can start again i can find another
set of internal states and identify its
blanket states and then take those steps
up the table and then start again and
recursively tile all the external states
so that now i've eliminated effectively
external states and replace them by the
internal and the blanket states of all
other things
and then on that view
what happens is that because
there's a um
a statistical
insulation or separation of internal and
external states by the blanket states
that means i can never see your internal
states i don't need it to know your
internal states
because everything that is
knowable about your internal states is
on the surface on your blanket states
well so now the picture that emerges is
an ensemble of things natural kinds
um that are coupled to each other
via their blanket states
no no no individual particle or person
or thing
and
will ever be have access to the internal
states of anything else
but there will be
um coupling of influences that are
mediated by the blanket states the
active states
and possibly the sensory states
mathematically you can actually have the
sensory states also influencing the
outside but the simplicity let's let's
assume that sensory states do not
influence external states uh it is just
the role of active states to actually
couple back to the outside you've
mentioned something extremely
interesting okay i'm gonna say one uh
one
um
exception to what he just said even
though i agree with everything you just
said except
with you know bearing one exception and
that is god god has access to your
internal states and
can perceive your internal states
because god is outside of time and space
and isn't limited by this
this
differentiation that we have have
created even though you know that he has
created
even though he has created it and he
chooses to not necessarily act
in a manner that would violate
your internal states even if he is
perceiving your internal state so he
could perceive your internal states
isn't changing your internal states
necessarily always
he can and sometimes he does you know if
it's you know the right thing to do but
normally
you would want to preserve multiplicity
because multiplicity of consciousness is
necessary to the creation of meaning
he doesn't want to just
make you do whatever he wants you to do
just by making you do it basically
turning you into a robot that he can
just control with you know remotely
that's not what he does because that
eliminates meaning
because it eliminates you as a
as a singularity into it unto yourself
as a separate from him and um if you're
not separate from him in any way then
there is no meaning so
there's uh this
when you're talking about consciousness
and people are like well is it
you are god
uh no you're separate from god okay
the answer is both
uh you are separate from me no we're all
one okay the answer is both because
the reality is is that if we didn't
intrinsically impact each other
event eventually
and then we
and we weren't one okay
part of the same system which is a
sentient
being in it of itself
then
what happens to you doesn't matter to me
and what happens to me shouldn't matter
to you
and
also
if we aren't separate
then
i don't matter
and you don't matter because you and i
don't exist so you need
separateness and oneness in order to
have meaning
and
if you have two parallel universes okay
in just i don't know the sean carroll
like
many worlds model or something not
claiming to perfectly understand it
because i kind of gave up a while back
but
you know as i understand it there's many
universes
and what happens in one does not really
influence another it may make another
but it doesn't influence the other so
there once you have two
parallel universes branching because of
this you know
a decision that has been made
they're separate from there and no
longer
relevant to each other so
in that model
what happens to one of them doesn't
impact the other at all
and
that model
um
is
is incorrect first of all but it
it it causes all kinds of logical
breakdowns okay when you take things to
its ultimate extreme which is why
his model doesn't work and um and many
other models don't work if it doesn't
um
if meaning is not the goal of the system
then
uh it doesn't it doesn't work there is
no
there's just a bunch of logical
breakdowns eventually but
there is one uniter that always makes it
so that
what happens to you should matter to me
what happens to me should matter to you
even if it's not as direct as you know
certain other relationships which it's
certainly not
you know
but um
that doesn't mean that it doesn't matter
it matters
and that is because there is a
uniting structure
to
all things that
that does
i guess uh
it's it it's
it isn't limited by these boundaries
that
uh carl fristen just talked about okay
where what happens to me doesn't matter
doesn't my internal state
is not visible to you
but
uh
that's doesn't mean that god my internal
state is not visible to god because if
my internal state is not visible to god
then
eventually you will have a breakdown in
uh in meaning and relevance essentially
and you have to have
a unifying structure to to all
uh
influence i guess
just really tough to understand but
um maybe not maybe it's intuitive for
you but it's regardless it's difficult
to find the words
but uh it's the only structure that does
transcend
boundaries in sensing
um of internal states
because
and the reason for this is because you
are
inside of them so it's like
the internal state of a cell
of a cell's molecules
does that matter to
like the dna of a cell is inside of a
cell
does that
the state of that dna matter to the cell
next to it
maybe maybe not but it's not perceivable
until it manifests in some you know
action
form but it still matters to the
organism that it's within because
that
structure that is higher up in this
nested hellonic you know hierarchy of
sentient artifacts or sentient
singularities
unites all the uh
all of the levels below so
um
and you can feel that you can feel the
state
of the
levels below you now not saying that you
have a direct
uh
like
picture
of what is happening inside your cells
but
the state of your cells will impact
the internal state of your cells will
impact
your internal state because it impacts
you know their external state yes and
and things like that but
uh
it's a different than
than another cell next to that cell
perceiving
uh an
action
happening by that cell
that it's next to
it's
more of like um
it's different it's like it's like a
feeling because it's inside
the cells inside of you the cells that
are next to each other not one
and because in it of themselves they are
united by the structure above which is
us as an organism and
uh but those cells inside of us are one
with us they are also separate but they
are also one whereas
the cell in
uh
in the cells inside you that are next to
each other are separate from each other
and they are not one with each other on
their level you have to up level in
order to
perceive the oneness and
uh that they that they have because you
have to see that they're part of
an organism but
we are the organisms so we already
perceive the oneness so i'm talking
about remember this is about perception
so from our perspective
we know that we are one with ourselves
and therefore our cells are one with
each other but
uh and that they are also separate but
from the perspective of the cells they
are not one with each other they are
separate from each other and it would
take
an an awareness of it of the upper level
structure of an organism that is uniting
the cells to be aware of and perceiving
of the structure that unites them into
one so
it's tough and uh sentient singularity
theory is about this it's about like the
perspective
that
uh that would then lead to the
constraints and degrees of freedom that
uh you know are kind of described in
the markov blankets of
uh free energy principle and
uh
it's
it's like
proceeding it's very tough
okay
this is the one rule of uh these mark
off blankets according to
fristen
we're going to talk about this
actual independence that definitively
specifies the markov blanket
it so happens that
all you need is the following rule
internal states can only influence
themselves and active states
external states can only influence
themselves
and sensory states that's all you need
so with that
condition in place you now immediately
have a markov blanket or a particular
partition
from that follows the conditional
independence therefore the
interpretation of the
um autonomous dynamics which is
a description of the trajectories or the
paths of the processes
taken by the active and the internal
states of a particular
of a particle
um
so
that means that it is actually
mathematically allowable
in the sense that you don't you do not
destroy that uh that mark off blanket or
the statistical properties of that mark
off blanket it is allowed of the sensory
states to influence uh active states and
you may be thinking well that's a bit
silly you know there's no way in which
my photoreceptors or my uh you know my
the cochlear in my ear materially affect
the outside
i think that's absolutely true so for
things like you and me
um
then you would not normally expect the
sensory states to influence the external
state
but that's not the case for much simpler
things
um when um when you look at much simpler
where
most of the dynamical influences the
coupling that we're talking about that
you'd write down in terms of the
differential equations the large line
equation
um
most of those influences this coupling
that he's talking about is what i call
entanglement
basically short range
so you know we can preclude action at a
distance for example if you're a single
cell
unless you're next to me i don't really
know what you're up to
i'm having to extrude here all sorts of
interesting things about long-range
electrochemical communication and
electrical gradients of the light but
let's just take
a bag of cells um that
that just diffuse stuff locally they
just
they touch each other and that's the
only way that they can they can
influence each other by
being proximate in some euclidean space
so everything short range now in this
situation you have a very different kind
of structure so here the cell the
sensory states are the cell surface
and when these active states that lie
underneath the cell surface
change the environment they do so by
pushing the cell surface um into the
external milieu and cause changes in the
sensory states the surface states of
other cells so
being a cell is probably a good example
of where your sensory states which just
are your surface states and actually do
all the heavy lifting in terms of
changing the outside the spatial
spatial relationship with all the other
cells that you're co-inhabiting a
particular organ
for example
so um you know it's a little bit
counterintuitive um but i think a really
interesting um sort of you know
thought experiment um and actually a
practical uh consideration when it comes
to
looking at the different ways in which
um
insights coupled to outsides and the
nature of interactions between the
internal states of something in the
external states of something
and we sort of take it for granted that
we can do actual distance you know uh
literally i can talk to you in canon
okay the reason why and i think i think
the reason why he's saying that this
that
our
perception our sensory states does not
influ directly influence the outside
world
um
the external states of
of reality
for us but they do for much simpler
structures he says so i'm not i
i think he gets into it uh there but i
don't think he's talking about even
cells he's talking about like
i think i think he gets into
you know particles uh and
things like that i need to double check
but
here's my my explanation for it is
exactly what i said earlier is that
basically like you cannot perceive
the entirety of what is going on on your
level
uh because you would need to be perce
perceiving of that which is happening on
the levels above you in order to
perceive the
the totality of what is uh
happening in on in your world because
your the level above you
knows to some degree
what
is what you are able to perceive and it
changes the world based on what you are
able to perceive because it wants to
show you certain things literally wants
to show you certain things that will
that are
that would give you a perspective that
is good for the
the uh the state of
the system as a whole the sentient
artifact as a whole so
when i say this be
in previous streams about how
our constraints and degrees of freedom
are within
with it when we're looking at space-time
our intrinsic constraint
is that we are always in our current
location we cannot change that we're
just always going to be on our current
location and we can go
closer towards
uh
our goal in space
and
we can also back up and go further from
our goal in space which is back the way
in which we came so if you want to go to
chick-fil-a chick-fil-a is the goal
in uh space-time and like you are in
your current location always along this
journey but you are can also go forwards
towards the goal but you can also go
backwards toward away from the goal
because you can go backwards towards
your house or whatever where you
originally started even though you have
the goal still of
um you know getting to chick-fil-a but
for some reason you've decided that
you're i don't know afraid or something
that uh and you're
not going forwards so
then your
that's your forward uh your
positive degree of freedom which is
forwards towards the goal that a
negative degree of freedom which is
backwards away from the goal
your intrinsic constraint which is your
current location which you cannot escape
and it is due to you you are the
constraint
that uh or you are the cause of that
constraint then there is an extrinsic
constraint that you are always within in
this journey and that is
in space time is time for us
it's just like um
uh this is the true four-dimensional
space time instead of length with height
and time it's forwards towards the goal
backwards away from the goal
uh your current location and time but
for the being that you are within
looking inward okay that's us looking
outward being inside of another sentient
artifact or something being looking
outward but
if you're that sentient artifact that we
are within looking inward kind of
announce
then
you have
your constraints and degrees of freedom
are not in space time they are in time
space now so everything is flipped
and you
have the ability to
maneuver
in time not in space because you are
space so it's like
saying like
move
you know within yourself it's you really
can't so you
time is like a vortex and you can
if you are the being above then you can
basically like
change how this vortex spins and how
fast it moves in certain locations in
order to influence time and so what it
does is it's trying to line up
what is happening
uh what what it wants to occur
in time with what you are having occur
in your space so you want to get to
chick-fil-a
and
let's say it wants you to meet your
future spouse on the way to chick-fil-a
and all of a sudden you get into a
fender bender with some girl and you're
some guy and you get this girl's
information because uh you just had a
fender bender with her and instead of
hating each other you end up falling in
love and getting married and um
this is
because literally sometimes
you could say god
or the universe as a sentient being
maneuvers in time by slowing down or
speeding up and you this isn't totally
imperceptible by you you cannot perceive
this you could they slow down time you
can't perceive it if they speed up time
you can't perceive it but doesn't
you you can see when certain things just
like happen it's like well what are the
odds of that
that that happened right then right
there and literally think about that
right then and there
okay
it's not just about space it's also
about time
so the time has been adjusted to match
up with your uh
where you are and
all of a sudden something happens
this is
only done by the being that is able to
it means that your perception
okay your sensory state
is influencing the world around you
because it's
the being above you
in the hierarchy of hold on
is changing the world around you based
on what you are perceiving
okay but you can't see that on your
level
and but you might be able to see that if
you're looking at much simpler
structures as
briston said
below us like you know i don't know if
you're going to look at like hadrons or
something like that you might be able to
see this type of
thing happening but you're that doesn't
mean you understand it but it means that
you can see that the percep the sensory
state
of
a being or of a particle
is influencing the world around it
but us
we assume that the sensory state of us
is not influencing the world around us
and that's not true so
people will very often get into well you
know
is if you look at the double slit
experiment it shows that you know our
perception influences you know reality
blah blah blah this is not real that
doesn't mean it's really understood by
people who are discussing it but this
isn't even exactly what i'm just talking
about i'm talking about
the world around you
the timing
that dictates when certain
structures are
in
position related to other structures
is being manipulated by the being above
you
in order to cause the intersection of
events
and
that is being done based on
your perceptions your sensory state
because
you need to sense
when the this event these events would
take place
okay
it's not
it's not doing it just based on your
actions having an impact on the outside
world
it's doing it based on your perceptions
of the world
and then it's it is making
is taking actions
that would change your world it's not
that your actions change the world it's
its actions change the world
but you can't see this on your level in
the periodicity of hellonic sentient
artifacts
so
it looks like just you know
your photon receptors your eyes
do not influence the world
necessarily when you're
and i'm not looking at things like
in quantum mechanics i'm talking about
just
you know normal
experience
it doesn't seem like it impacts the
world but it does
because your world
is also
a sentient artifact
that
you
it's it is a
multiplicity of sentient artifacts that
you are interacting with or sentient
singularities and you're all within
a singular sentient singularity or
sentient artifacts that is making
conscious choices based on what you are
perceiving
not even what you're doing sometimes
also what you're doing but also what
you're perceiving because it has to
it has to maneuver within time which
means it's not just about what actions
you're currently taking
it's also about what actions you might
take
which is based on your perceptions
uh that you currently have so what you
your sensory states
and
uh
it
what this
means is that there's no such thing as
probability from an objective
perspective there is just
uh determinism and that that determinism
is based on choice
and your choices are constrained or or
are dictated by certain constraints and
degrees of freedom that manifest based
on
a number of factors but
um there is no probability probability
is an illusion
okay it's about you predicting what will
happen what another being will do
okay
before they do it or you know
beyond them doing it
but it doesn't mean that
uh it's not actually
deterministic because as soon as they
make a choice
it's no longer
uh 33 he's going to take uh you know i
don't know like he's going to
go to college and and 66 percent he's
not going to go to college
it's he's
there is
there is no um
there's nothing almost and then there is
100 percent he's going to college or 100
he's not going to college but
prior to this you can
uh
you can make predictions but that
doesn't mean that it's not deterministic
it's not
probab reality is not probabilistic
your ability to
model reality
is probabilistic
you it can it can use probability which
is about
it's just geometry really but it's
it's not
that the world is probabilistic we think
about this all the time in quantum
mechanics is like oh you know when
you're looking at electrons and you
can't see where it is and whatever it's
like
oh it's based in probability reality is
probabilistic no it's not probabilistic
your your model of reality
in your
markup blanket basically in your mind
is probabilistic but
it's actually not
there's no such thing as probability
outside of an internal
mental model of
reality
which is really just a bunch of mental
a bunch of minds modeling but
the because reality is actually
composed of a bunch of minds that make
choices
and
uh or act in accordance with um
you know
a
deterministic algorithm which would be
like instincts
okay sometimes you can make choices and
go against your instincts and that's
actual choices and those are those are
deterministic
cause deterministic outcomes and then
also
uh if you don't make any choices and
you're just acting on instincts
basically you're just letting an
algorithm run it's also deterministic so
there is no escaping this whatsoever
reality is deterministic
it also allows for choice because choice
is part of determinism
uh
and
um
but probability is
reality is not probably probabilistic
it's just
the interpretation of you know
in then having your internal model of
reality could be probabilistic
but not
actual reality that's always
deterministic
and um
that is something we don't yet fully
understand but it's i just felt like
mentioning because he's talking about
probabilities in multiple parts of this
uh stream and
probability is not it's not fundamental
it's
it's just emergent within a mind that is
modeling the world around it
but it's and it's because of the limit
that it has
where like uh fristen says you can't
perceive the internal state of another
um
from you okay
and that's true of us
and another and another human like me as
a human and you as a human i cannot
perceive what is happening inside of
your mind
i'm not cannot perceive what you are
perceiving
i can only perceive one your actions
once you do them
but
the being above you
above us the universe god can perceive
what you are perceiving and can make
adjustments to reality based on it and
we will not be aware of those
um
easily so like he said
uh
the sensory state of simple structures
can influence reality
but not of us that's not true it's just
we can't perceive it
okay that was cool
um
okay
next
i'm gonna go a little bit quick because
i have about 15 minutes i'm trying to
end
this
but this is uh kurt talking about how uh
about how the free energy principle
about how the free
energy principle is inscrutable which
means
you can't understand it it's just not
understandable and i'll explain why this
is the case in a minute
between our sensory states and our
active states that is not um
a gift
of very simple um cellular-like
structures or automata
that can't interpret signals um will be
subject to or be sensitive to
some influences uh at a distance just so
you know or people who are listening and
if this wasn't obvious enough the free
energy principle is famous for or
perhaps infamous for being somewhat
inscrutable for people who have a
physics background or math background
what would be the minimum prerequisites
this is how i like to conceptualize the
podcast before i interview someone i
think about okay what are all the pieces
of knowledge i need to know prior to
interviewing them so obvious example is
let's say qft you need to understand
classical mechanics laurence variants
quantum mechanics perhaps bundle theory
if you want to understand yang mils and
so on properly so what would be the
prerequisites for someone to properly
understand the free energy principle
let's say if they have a math or physics
background it wouldn't be
it would be probably much less than
you'd expect to encounter
a university i think you'd certainly
need to know
um sort of you know
the basics of variational calculus and
it would be really nice if you
understood where a labrador
came from um
and uh to understand the simplicity of
action you know basically you know
exactly hamilton's principal beast
action how that inherits from path
intervals of lagrangians and uh how that
arises from um
dynamical systems theory of a very
simple sort where you can write down any
random dynamical system as you know a
stochastic differential equation or a
large value equation
i think
that's probably quite sufficient you
know what um
what you would need i think
to
appreciate all the interpretational
richness afforded by
what happens to
the paths of least action when you have
a mark of blanket you need to know a
little bit of probability theory you
need to know what a conditional
distribution is you need to know uh the
import you know what have an intuition
as to what is meant by
model evidence for example or marginal
likelihood so okay
i was very good at probability in school
it was like one of the things i was
ridiculous at um and
i took a class it was one of the few
math classes i actually took in
school was required for financial a
finance degree
and was about it was probability and um
and i aced it i think it was the top of
the class and i mean like when i say top
i mean like the top not like
i was i was so good that like once i got
my wisdom teeth out and i had to take
the test like a couple days after
everybody else and everybody had gotten
their tests back i knew that and um
and i
was allowed to take the test
like
uh
like alone they at a at a different time
which was a few days later because like
i said i got my wisdom teeth out and i
i didn't finish the last problem because
i knew that if i had done it i was going
to get 100 on the test and it was my
first test in the class and
i
so i hadn't proven that i was like good
enough to get 100 and i
thought that i would be seen as cheating
so i on the last question i just started
doing it and i just stopped and i just
never finished it so i got
every other question correct except the
last one
and that's not to brag i'm just saying
like
this is probably why i can understand a
lot of this
um and
i just have a natural kind of ability to
visualize proper
prop probability which is really like
it's like geometric relationships but
it's not
actually real like i said it's just me
modeling reality and it doesn't exist in
actuality um
so
uh
so like if you think about marbles and
like there's like three marbles three
green marbles and a
thing of nine marbles and there's six
red marbles and three green marbles
inside of a jar and
you go and you're
blindfolded and you reach your hand and
you have to pick out a marble and you
know what are the odds that you pick out
a green one versus a red one and
obviously the probabilistic odds are
that you pick out you know
uh
one third
it's that your
the likelihood that you pick out a green
one would be 33 percent but likelihood
that you pick out a red one would be you
know 66 percent
but
in reality
which one you grab let's say you reach
your hand and you're like feeling around
you grab there's you can feel two
distinct marbles but you can't tell
which one's red and which one's
green as soon as you make the choice to
go with one of those two marbles it's
now all of a sudden
it's a hundred percent going to be
a green one or 100 going to be a red one
assuming that one of those was green and
one of those was red but it's just your
mental model
that is
frames the world in probabilistic sense
but the reason why he's what he said
here what was great i love this he said
the the prerequisites are much less than
what you would think and people have
told me since the start of this project
you don't understand you couldn't have
done this because like you haven't even
taken a physics class you haven't done
you couldn't have done this because you
haven't read penrose's you know road to
the reality you haven't done this
because you don't know what
uh you know this equation is there uh
you haven't memorized maxwell's
equations whatever
they've always placed these various
uh
like assumed prerequisites on top of
this work and
fristen is correct in saying like it's
much less than you would have expected
because
but it's also much more it's like much
more than what you would have expected
but much less because it's much less of
what you would have expected but much
more of what you wouldn't have expected
to be necessary as necessary and that's
really what it is it's superposition so
you need to have had a lot more
of
what you wouldn't have expected which
uh
then what uh
than what most people would have
expected you would have expected like
physics and computer science and maybe
some mathematics and
uh
the reality is is that you don't need
these things very much and
uh you know to develop this deeply you
would need to eventually learn some of
this stuff to really but only for the
sake of relating your work to the other
things that are currently known by the
scientific you know community not for
the sake of building what you can build
as the ultimate structure of what is
the free energy principle
what would be the free energy principle
mark off blankets within it you know and
sentient singularity theory and which uh
has you know
sentient singularities within it or uh
you know quanta of
context or quanta of consciousness which
is like when to interact with each other
and create a moment but
uh what
the reason why it's inscrutable
meaning like
both of these sentient singularity
theory and
uh
you know the free energy principles are
just it's not understandable
by so many especially those in the
academic world who are
you know especially physicists i would
imagine
you would see this
that people in computer science have an
easier time people even in biology would
have probably an easier time
neuroscience maybe have an easier time
as long as they're not too focused on
the brain
but physics would physicists would
really struggle and that's why
physicists are really struggling with
physics more so than any other uh you
know group of academicians
is because
they are
is because what i'm about to explain is
that
when reality is a bunch of sentient
beings or conscious beings or minds
and physics does assumes that that's not
the case then first of all you're
starting from the wrong place but
when it is a bunch of sentient beings or
minds
understanding fundamental reality means
understanding mind understanding
consciousness understanding sentience
and to do that
most
act most correctly which i mean you
really need to get this right if you're
going to understand it at all
is you would look to
where you can learn the most about
that structure about a sentence about a
consciousness about a mind
and if you do that by looking to
second-hand information that is being
taught in school on a blackboard or uh
on a youtube video even
or in a book
and that is where you're looking to
understand sentience instead of looking
inside yourself to understand sentience
mind consciousness
you're already starting
wrong because you're basically trusting
secondhand information over firsthand
information which if as soon as you
really understand this mean you know
that you can't do that and as soon as
you do you're screwed
this is i'll talk about this in a minute
this is how people can literally
manipulate
your minds and how you can lose your
mind a bit but
uh especially even when you're studying
consciousness
if you're just listening to other people
talk about consciousness and you start
taking other people's word for it
over your own personal experience
that's first-hand
information which is what experience is
then you're going to start to lose lose
it
or at least it's possible and
uh you know
michael levin uh when he was on uh kurt
janmungle's uh channel just uh talking
about his work he said that
the investigation of consciousness is a
firsthand um
endeavor
okay
it is experienced
it's you experiencing yourself
that and and paying attention to it and
that is how you can understand
fundamental reality
but if you go to outside of yourself to
understand fundamental reality you're
looking
not at
directly at a sentient
at sentience or consciousness to
understand fundamental reality you're
looking at
kind of like a
like um
a reduced watered-down
version of
or explanation or model of it because as
soon as you turn something into
an image or or
you translated verbally or anything like
that
audibly all of a sudden you've reduced
the amount of information
experience though is experience and you
thinking about yourself
experiencing yourself and that and
self-awareness coming from that
that is where you actually understand
reality and to those who have
done that to a sufficient
degree free energy principle and
sentient singularity theory are going to
be intuitive
but to those who go outside of
themselves
to understand
whether or not this is true and they're
trying to relate what he's is being
described in the free energy principle
and sentient singularity theory to what
is in this textbook in this textbook in
this textbook
they're it's going to be inscrutable
but if you're trying to take what is
being described in sentient singularity
theory and in carl fristan's free energy
principle and you're trying to relate it
to your personal experience that's where
it's going to become intuitive
and academicians especially
those in academia especially those in
physics
are going to be probably the first ones
to go and see if whether or not the free
energy principle lines up with something
you know
written by another physicist
which you don't even know that's true
and uh it's like you're you don't want
it's like that game of telephone you
don't you want to just hear the original
message you don't want to hear you know
the message after it's been said
uh you know in a chain
of
50 people
the odds of you getting the correct
message from that is just not nearly as
likely and imagine that that was across
multiple languages
and also some people wrote it down and
some people said it verbally and some
people played trades to get the next
person to guess it and all instead of
just you know you hearing it from the
source but the thing is is that you are
the source
and
that is
where you're going to
see free energy principle become
intuitive and
you're going to be like
listen to him describing markov blankets
and you not being able to influence um
the internal state of another being
uh or sense the internal state of
another being
separate from you like you know i don't
know your classmate you can't sense what
is going on inside of you can't sense
what they're sensing
right and if you think about that
it's going to be intuitive but if you're
like i'm going to go look up in a book
i don't know what book yet but a book of
whether or not
you know you can whether or not a a
a cell can
sense
what another cell is sensing like
uh to determine whether or not the free
energy principle makes sense or is right
you're not gonna
this is not gonna work you're going to
misinterpret
uh and you might as well just like
not do it
at all
but this is why to some people it's
inscrutable and to some people it's
intuitive people who it's intuitive to
are
trying to
they're checking
sentient singularity theory and the
things that come from it
and the lessons that come from it and
it's free energy principle and the
lessons that come from it the models
that come from it with their personal
experience
and to those people this is intuitive
and it but if
the people who are already relying like
what kurt said is like what is the
is you know what is the prerequisite
knowledge
the prerequisite requirement is that you
are a sentient being
and that you are checking
it based on your
the lessons from these two theories
with your personal experience
primarily that doesn't mean you don't
also check it with other things but you
hold
what lines up with your personal
experience above what lines up with some
you know fact in a textbook
always
or some equation in a textbook
and um
but if you're assuming that there is
coursework that would be necessary to
understand the free energy principle
then you've already
put
second-hand information above first-hand
understanding
in in your rel in your attempt to try
and understand this and you've already
destroyed
like
any hope of you truly
you know having an intuitive
understanding of the free energy
principle or sentient singularity theory
you don't need school
to understand this
school can teach you things that are
known
that then you can later see line up with
the lessons from these two
theories but they're not
that is not whatever that information
comes from that is not as important
and should not be put as high in the
hierarchy
of of determining whether or not
something is true kind of
um
as your first hand experience
so when i say
consciousness
exists
and you're and
and somebody is like
uh
or choices exist
and somebody says
choices don't exist
and you're just a leaf you know like a
sam harris leaf in a river or whatever
but like consciousness doesn't even
exist some people
i i as i've said on here before some
people have come on to my discord who
are
trying to get their phd in philosophy of
consciousness
their thesis was arguing that
consciousness doesn't exist what they're
doing is they're placing
models
of information processing
that have been watered down
that are watered-down reductions of what
is you know actually happening inside
your mind
above their own personal experience
and then saying because those models
exist and there isn't and they process
information in a certain way outside of
a conscious
outside of consciousness not even
thinking about the fact that they are a
consciousness who had to write down the
models or another consciousness did
they
are now coming to this crazy conclusion
that invalidates their entire existence
they have basically thought their way
into
like
you know
into
delusion
and
uh
and it is because they put first-hand
second-hand information above first-hand
information
you cannot do that
in
any attempt to understand consciousness
because everything
because you are a consciousness okay
you can do that in an attempt to
understand
airplanes
because airplanes are not conscious and
you are not an airplane
but if you're trying to understand that
conscious beings
and you are a conscious being
then you are the greatest evidence
and and
uh to look to
in order to understand
whatever it is that you're looking at
that you're also trying to understand
another conscious being but if you're
just
looking at you know airplanes trying to
understand airplanes don't look to
yourself as like
an attempt to understand airplanes
because you're not an airplane
but
this does work with consciousness and as
soon as you
do this
where you put do
where as soon as you put secondhand
information about firsthand information
meaning like you put what you learned in
school above what you have experienced
in real life you're going to lose your
mind
and we see this with people all around
us and we're going to
talk about this
for a minute so
i thought this was interesting real
quick
and then we'll get to that discussion um
and then i have some questions that i
have to answer i'll get to the chat i
promise
and then uh we'll go
but
here
so
if if we are
um coming back to this picture of uh
some mathematical universe that i've now
tiled with multiple markov blankets
encapsulating or defining lots of
particles um and basically we
inhabit a universe that is constituted
by things like us and initially you know
mum and dad and brothers and sisters and
then you know
peers at school
that means that our models of our lived
or experienced world
have to have models of other in it which
means you need to be able to
disambiguate
between sensations caused by others and
sensations that you caused as a
well
this right here is that
this is the universe
composed only of markov blankets
basically or
or sentient singularities or sentient
artifacts and the you have the hierarchy
of these sentient artifacts
and
each
basically
you have
these
this is a
a
sentient artifact or a markov blanket
kind of
and um
it is a calculating structure that is
self-calculating so you can see that the
values are changing based on what we is
the input but the input is always one
and um because you are your own input in
any kind of like sensible
uh sense and then you've got the
perspectives here the definition of
those perspectives here
and um you've got some of the math going
on which is just basically you're taking
information and you're in a symmetrical
structure which means like all of what's
happening here has to be symmetrical
with
that so
you have symmetrical calculation
and um
uh
and then you take the information that
is internally calculated and uh
you add it together and then you also
multiply it so this is multiplication
this is addition uh simultaneously until
you get a self-reflection which we'll
get into later but
this
is this right here is a bunch of these
there's one there's one
well
there's one
there's one and they're just stacked and
layered and entangled in such a way
and um
that they're connected
and
you can see that
it's still calculating
okay
in
very
specific way
and if you change here and you go zero
all of a sudden this is all zeros
because
this is all connected you input one and
there you go this is exactly what he
just described it's tiling
okay
tiling of the world
according to
like these mark off blankets which are
composed of four primary perspectives
of inside outside separate and oneness
and that function
according to
internal external
sensing and acting
uh as the four-part partition of the
functionality of this
uh
for of these of this one sentient
singularity that is composed of four
primary perspectives
okay
fascinating did he even use the word
tiling
okay
so
kurt
deals with understanding trying to
understand a lot of different
theories of everything
and
in doing so
you know especially when these theories
are primarily centered around
consciousness in the end which is any
accurate one would be
it's very easy to kind of just start
like to have an existential crisis
and uh i will say to kurt like
specifically and anybody else who is who
is experiencing some kind of like
existential crisis of like do i exist
does my wife exist does my do my friends
exist does god exist as
does anything exist
does anyone exist
it just like take chill out it's okay
like and know that you're not the alone
in going through this
and uh in it in that of itself
like knowing that
you're not alone in going through that
means
others exist and you exist
because if you are not alone
then like there's others who are going
through that as well and i can tell you
that that's true
and um
and
obviously you don't know whether or not
i exist
and i don't know whether or not you
exist you could be a construction
but
by who
you know it's like i didn't construct
you
at least not initially
but
because there are parts of you that i
don't know and and
and as soon as i do know them that
doesn't mean that i understand even what
what you're saying there are math
you know mathematical statements that
you know kurt makes that i don't
understand
because i don't that i just don't know
it's not even that i don't understand
them i don't know them because i
didn't go to school for mathematical
physics
but that
that information came from somewhere
came from someone
that's not me
so i assume also that
there's others that exist not just me
but also
it'd be wildly inefficient
for
you to be the sole
existent sentience
in
your
digital world
okay in your simulation i guess
it would not make any sense it'd be
extremely
boring
and it would be extremely inefficient
and prime and here's the thing it would
be isolating of you from others and
that destroys meaning
meaning was the purpose of the creation
of ex of multiplicity of
existence so if you exist
and you didn't create
everything else that you experienced
then there had to be someone else who
did and the creation of multiplicity is
for the sake of meaning because there is
no meaning outside of multiplicity and
if if you're god and you're all there is
there is no
meaning to you to your existence
you don't feel meaningless
you are meaningless if you're god and
there's no no one else beyond creation
and god didn't feel meaningless he was
meaningless
and he felt meaningless but he also knew
he was meaningless
beyond creation
god
didn't
feel lonely he was
alone
and he knew it
you can feel lonely in this in this
existence but that doesn't make you
actually alone
it's just like a lie
god knew he was alone
he knew
there was no one else he knew he was
meaningless
he knew there was no meaning
at all
and
there's logical reasons for that you
know if you if all that exists is
sentience then all that meat matters is
sentience and you know your impact on
other sentences so you know
if you're aware that you are all there
is and that you are alone then you are
aware that sentience is all that matters
but that you are the only sentience and
so
uh
and you don't matter to any other
sentences and therefore you are
meaningless
you are meaningless
you are alone
not just lonely
you are lonely you're the loneliest the
loneliest person to have ever existed
was gone at a certain point
so it's the least lonely person to have
ever to ever be when i say person
meaning like having personhood having
sentience not like a human
but
simultaneously the loneliest
and
the the
least lonely because he knows everyone
now that now that multiplicity has been
created
he's was the most meaningless okay or
had the least meaning again no meaning
prior to creation
but now
has all meaning because everyone out who
exists other than himself
was created by him
so
we all owe everything
which means
he is the most meaningful
so
my point is is that there are
there are
logical reasons why
multiplicity of consciousness exists
even though
sometimes
you question everything along with in
your attempt to question everything you
you question your own
world away
and i did this you know kurt says in
here he says you know i felt horrible
because i'm questioning whether or not
my wife exists
and i have that exact i've had that
exact same experience where i looked at
my wife
and i mean my it was my uh girlfriend at
the time but and i've looked even done
this sense but
don't really do this anymore uh in any
kind of like real
way but prior to getting married there
was moment there were moments along this
journey where i looked at all my friends
and my parents and my siblings and my
uh my
uh girlfriend who i now married
and i have just been like
do you are you even ring
are you a bot in a game and i'm the only
player
and
that's okay to think to question that
it's also wrong to
inevitab to to to
to deduce that you've made some error if
that is the final
like
if that is uh your final conclusion
there's so many reasons why that is not
the case but it is
understandable why you would question
that and i've done that so many times
and it is a nerve-wracking
experience to do it honestly to be like
i'm a i mean i wasn't even married yet
and i'm like i mean if you are married
it might be even harder on you or psyche
but
uh to not be married and to be like
am i about to marry a bot
like that is a
and to really think about it is
it's tough it's a tough thing but uh i
can tell you
you're not alone in this and
um
which means that like
the inevitable conclusion of that uh
questioning that line of questioning is
that
you should assume that the other beings
around you are sentient
uh that appear to be sentient or
sentient
um there are logical reasons
from so many different
uh
i guess like angles that that that that
is true
and um
but ultimately
if sentience is all there
is
and sentience is all that matters that
means that the perp there's purpose and
meaning to this world that we are in
and
uh if there is then multiplicity of
consciousness is
the generator of that and therefore
uh you should not think that you are
alone in the universe
you're not the universe is not even
uh
it is in it of itself scented like there
is no
escaping of this
you're much less lonely than you ever
could
uh be
so or could have imagined i guess
like
it's just impossible
but i understand it's tough man
anything in my head just that thought
and i've because i'm on this podcast and
i've entertained many ideas it's
extremely taxing to do so because i try
to take different people's points of
views
seriously
and perhaps i shouldn't but i feel like
in order to give them a fair shake i
need to embody them in some way shape or
form so if they say well all is mind for
example that's the idealists
i'm trying to imagine what would that be
like and if someone's a materialist well
what did it mean that this was dead and
it somehow emerged that we have
consciousness either way the point of
that is to say i've been feeling like
for almost a year and a half now just in
a void not sure what is true and what's
not true that's fine i can deal with
that except that that led me to this
spiraling of such
it was probably the most terrifying
experience i've ever had in my life
and it took me weeks and i'm still
recovering from it where i felt like
shoot
am i all that exists and then just that
thought alone i'm like i don't want to
believe that that could be the case and
i remember looking at my wife and
thinking is my wife even real how
much of an imbecile and how ungrateful
and how foolish is it and how
that i would even think that i feel bad
that i would even entertain that thought
oh my gosh i'm scared i don't want to go
to the hospital because i felt like if i
was to truly accept that thought i could
i was on the brink of just losing it
into an insensitive spiral
i became extremely scared of myself and
i think that i'm the type of person i am
an anxious person
and i
am the type of person that tends to
obsess over thoughts
so then i started to obsess over this
and for the past couple weeks i was so
scared so scared of my own mind so
almost like a hypochondriac for mental
disorders where i didn't want to even
look up what's the definition of
schizophrenia or psychosis was because i
was afraid that i would see the signs
everywhere for example
a few days ago or about a week ago i
remember generally we all speak to
ourselves in our own heads and sometimes
i use the phrase so i don't like that or
i like that i use the word i in my own
internal monologue but sometimes the
word yeah you can do this you can do
this so sometimes you use i and
sometimes they use you
and i imagine we all do that it's
colloquially okay to exchange those two
however then i thought oh shoot
what if i felt distance from my thought
what if the one that's saying you is a
thought speaking to me like a
schizophrenic may hear
oh my gosh oh my gosh i don't want to
hear this and i was so afraid that i
felt derealized and depersonalized when
you mentioned parkinson's earlier that
the difference between the model and
then the data it that didn't strike
okay
i don't have that much time so i i can't
go too deeply into this even though i
want to and but let me explain
i understand exactly where he's coming
from i've been there this is
difficult to navigate it's difficult to
navigate this space of consciousness
but the thing is is what's kurt might be
in actually a harder place than me
because i purposely avoided other
people's work along this journey
because i didn't want my mind to just
get lazy and start taking other people's
word for it even just being like that
sounds good i'm gonna take that
and um and i know that my mind
could do that because that's what we do
you know we're just like if we're like
we don't want to do the math of why the
earth would be a sphere
at least from outside of it
that's another discussion
then we would just take
you know the word of someone else
because oh that makes sense with
satellites and like ever other things
that i'm aware of in my mind but so
we'll accept it as true even though none
of us have ever been outside of the
earth
and unless we are astronauts so we're
always taking somebody's word for it and
that
like
this this is something your mind can do
and you got to be really careful of it
when it comes to consciousness because
you cannot take
the word
of
sec or you cannot take second-hand
information above first-hand experience
in this journey and if you do you will
lose it
you really will you cannot
take
your
uh
like
information that you have figured out by
looking up uh definitions of
schizophrenia or anything like that
um
or
uh
as as as basically like
the determining evidence as to whether
or not you have lost it
and
uh
you
if you do start looking to other sources
outside of yourself
to validate or invalidate your own
existence
then you
are almost it's like you have chosen to
invalidate your own existence
and
maybe not realized it
you can't do this
and there are certain instances in which
you can do this where it creates little
moments of of derealization of your of
yourself
as a sentient feeling entity that
actually has self-control but then there
are certain topics where you cannot do
this
maybe you can do this with climate
change where like you don't know what's
going on with climate change so you look
it up and you're like i'm taking that
guy's word for it even though
you know you have no idea
and you can't relate that with your
first-hand personal experience in any
way that really matters um and so you
take on second-hand information and you
put it above your first hand experience
and um
uh
and then you know you can become this
like
i don't know this like broken mind that
can buy a house on the beach and then
also you know
come
preach about how sea levels are going to
rise 30 feet in the next like 30 years
it's like well you just bought a beach
house on the mansion do you
a mansion on the beach do you really
like think that
sea levels are gonna rise in 30 years
but
this
there's a brokenness happening and it is
because of the prioritization of
secondhand information above firsthand
information
and
it's just momentary in certain things
like that but it can be all-encompassing
when it comes to with you know your
personhood or the personhood of others
if you truly believe that no one else
exists
that is a pathway to absolute like
insanity
and
uh
and and in a very like serious way if
you truly believe that you don't exist
you will act in a manner in which like
you have removed you you have no more
agency you gave it up
and see people tell you you have no free
will it's like i have no free will
that is like
it's
i mean that's free will is complicated
because you kind of you have to know
that you have instincts but you are in
order to understand where your freedoms
are but if you you truly believe that
you couldn't make any choices ever
then you
even though your experiences as someone
who makes
choices if i tell you you have instincts
and you have choices that you can make
that can go against those instincts and
then you think about your own personal
experience and you're like yeah i really
have had like a lot of drives and like
uh
before to to eat this and act in that
way but like in doesn't go along with
you know how i think things objectively
should be done
and it creates a conflict in my mind
it's like your first-hand experience is
now validating the fact
that you have instincts and you have
choices it's like
okay
but if you look to some book in your
life and it basically says you're
nothing but chemical reactions
and uh
and
and that's it and you have no ability to
make actual choices
and for or for some reason you have
deduced and that gets you to you know
consciousness doesn't exist and you're
writing your thesis about how
consciousness doesn't exist it's like
who's writing the thesis about
consciousness about about how
consciousness doesn't exist this can be
bad
and um
and i don't it it pains me a lot because
i'm like well you know i'm teaching
about consciousness and uh because
that's what this theory is about but i
don't really think that you can learn
about consciousness from a second hand
uh
you know
source and actually get it and not
misinterpret it and kind of eventually
like
do you realize your own existence
so my advice to anybody listening to my
theory
or carl kristen's work or any other
theory ctmu
that is about consciousness
is
you
your experience has to be the
primary
data set by which all other
day
data are
compared and if they don't it doesn't
uh align with what your personal
experience is then
disregard it
don't think that your personal
experience is wrong personal experience
is right
and um
if you have to do this you absolutely
have to you know i've said on here
before that there i asked myself like
you know
first isaac asimov wrote a short story
called last question and ends with let
there be light it's it's interesting you
should look it up it's about like a
tech uh an ai and like basically
creating universes
and so i asked myself what is the first
question
and i found there actually is a first
and the first question
when you ask you say what is the first
question
the answer is what is the first question
it answers itself with itself
and
then
you get to uh what is the second
question
and it is what is the truest thing that
i know
and the second answer which is the
answer to that question
the answer to the second question is
i am
so
what is the first question
it's the first question
the first answer is what is the first
question
second question is what is the truest
thing that i know the second answer is i
am
and this this is like the fibonacci
sequence one one two three it's like the
first one repeats twice and then you get
it kind of creates the
the
second question and or the
the ability to have the second question
and then is answered uh as the third
piece of
their perspective or the fourth
perspective but
it is the uh
it's like the second answer to the
second question which would be i am you
are the truest thing that you know
everything starts with that that you
exist i am
you are
and um
and anything that invalidates that
is false
and it must be treated as false
or you will
lose it
you will lose yourself literally lose
yourself
and uh you see this a lot with people
who are in like politics these days
where people have a meme called npcs
non-player characters it's like just
everybody's becoming bots
and they're not always bots they're bots
in specific instances but they're
increasingly bots and the reason why is
because it's people who are trusting
second-hand sources of information above
their first-hand experience
say oh well you know the
uh
everyone is is
is racist and sexist and this and and
whatever you know you mean by that
doesn't matter it means something
negative
uh
and then you hear that again and again
and again you've learned it in schools
and and
and that these people are oppressed and
these people don't need uh these people
men don't need women and women don't
need men you know it's like if you start
taking all this stuff again and again
and again and again
the second-hand information above your
first-hand information which is like do
women need men
yeah
do men need women yeah your first-hand
experience would absolutely tell you
that you were birthed by a woman if
you're a man
then men need women
because
you needed your mother your mother to
give birth to you but if you start
taking
uh
you know someone's worth that like men
don't need women
and it's like or women don't need men
it's like you're taking some exterior
word from this and you're not thinking
about your first hand experience
um don't do that because the more you do
that the more you will lose yourself but
if you do that with consciousness you
can totally lose yourself
in like one or two you know
um misconcluded
ideas
uh so i have to go here in a minute but
um
uh i thank everybody for the support in
the chat i'm going to answer these last
things because uh someone had asked me
about this in
theory of everyone discord
could you differentiate sentient
non-sentient parts of reality
um
yes
non-sentient parts of reality would not
be in this hierarchy of nested
structures right here of like a hadron
is an assembly of quarks an atom is an
assembly of hadrons uh
a molecule is an assembly of atoms
cell is an assembly of molecules
families and assembly of organisms
etc so this nested helonic
periodicity anything outside of it is uh
non-sentient and this is
each one is within the next an atom
hadrons are inside of atoms atoms are
inside of molecules molecules are inside
of cells cells are inside of organisms
organisms are inside of families
families are inside of castes casts are
inside of technology or you could say
each one makes up the next hadrons make
up atoms atoms make up molecules
molecules make up cells cells make up
organisms organisms make up families
families make up casts casts make up
technology and anything outside of that
is going to be a nonsentience
um okay
uh
is every split in the unity
feeling something yes every object every
sentient singularity within the singular
sentient singularity of existence itself
feels that's by definition that is that
is
feeling is the finality of thought or
information processing around the self
so it's self aware
is is a byproduct of self-awareness
feeling so
everyone feels
kind of not everything not you know
chairs do not feel but the molecules
within it
feel
um like this does not exist objectively
it only exists subjectively this is a
remote control for the lights
it's made of molecules they do
exist
objectively
and uh
and the atoms that make up those
molecules also exist objectively
and
because they're part of this periodic
structure
but you can't be like
remote controls and get anywhere
remote controls make up
what you can see like remote controls
are makeup made up of what plastic
springs
rubber
glass
you know like batteries that are you're
just eventually going to get to rock
bottom but
it all of those are just subjective
there isn't uh really an objective
perspective to look at things at
um so you have to go in that periodicity
that i showed i don't have the time to
get too into it i wanted to get more
into it but this went a bit long um but
i will
talk to you more about it um and also
this will all be in my paper that's
coming soon
uh
is a story
and i'm creating my head a separate
cluster of awareness no only god's
thoughts are sentient you are sentient
thought
but um
but it's not even right to say thoughts
are sentient because
it's like that's not really
true it's like you're a player in a
thought but
our concrete
reality
is the thoughts of the being above us so
like god's thoughts or the universe's
thoughts are experienced by us as
concrete reality
even though our thoughts are not
experienced as by god as concrete
reality or by us as concrete reality
they are just internal states but
because we are inside of a being above
us in the hierarchy of nested
periodicity of sentience
anything in that is happening in the
mind
above us which is a mind in it of itself
that's what it is a universal mind the
thoughts of the universal mind
are literally
experienced by us as material reality
it's higher their thoughts are higher
than us
in the hierarchy
and um
that doesn't mean you can't influence
them it just means that like we
experience them as hard reality you know
you can influence hard reality
but uh you know you can push
a dresser across the room or whatever
but like you're gonna
can't just like think that dresser is
not there and it's not there
because
the thought in the mind that we're
within is thinking that that dresser is
there so it's there
um
but
it's not a separate cluster of awareness
um
there's only sentient beings and
really and like they each have like
various awarenesses but a thought is not
a separate
sentient being
uh
yeah the relationships between sentient
beings can be the thoughts of the mind
that we're within
so think about your thoughts as a mind
like imagine the universe is a mind and
it's having thoughts and we are inside
that mind
that processes
that are occurring within the mind that
we are within are going to be
experienced as hard reality to us
because they are like you're inside of
it
um how do you decide was an individual
and what is not
uh what i said earlier that periodicity
is uh
of
those composite structures
are those are sentiences
and uh so hadron may be an atom
definitely molecule cell organism
family
um
uh
cast and and technology and some half of
these
they're really four beings or four sides
of this periodicity each
but this these eight periods can be
split into four and four and four of
them maneuver in space via individuals
and for the maneuver in time via
lineages so an organism is maneuvering
in space as an individual but it's
lineage it's really part of a lineage
structure is actually maneuvering in
time
via lineage of
like chain a chain of individuals so
uh and they're really the same thing you
are not just one individual you are the
tip of the sphere of a lineage that you
know is behind you
so it's a superposition structure but uh
which one is an individual
uh an individual lineage is also an
individual it's kind of but it's also
it's also a chain
but
you are also an individual but you're
also you know an assembly of cells so
it's
an individual is
uh wherever being can be
self-aware and meaning feeling it has
feelings if it doesn't have feelings
it's not an individual but if it has
feelings like real feelings
then
it is an individual
so with that thank you everyone and uh
would you describe god as god is the
uh singular sentience that is existence
itself existence is a sentient being all
of existence
and uh
yeah that is gone with that hit the like
button please share this um i do have to
go but uh i really appreciate everybody
on here definitely check out the entire
interview with kurt and
um and carl fristen i'm going to watch
the next uh
um the other stream with carl fristen
that was uh older but it it's like three
and a half hours long or something like
that and we'll see if there's more to
talk about but his work is incredible
and uh
to curt if kurt ever watches this or
anyone else who is also investigating
these theories of conscious that involve
consciousness
you
exist
and you are the evidence of your own
existence and do not believe anything
that violates your personal experience
even if i say it if i say something and
it does not jive with what your personal
experience is
then don't believe it
put it into a separate like basket of
facts
or not facts but of of
you know bits of information that you've
heard that may or may not be true
but
the things that you put into the basket
of
true must align with your personal
experience
and that is how you
keep your
sanity
uh when you do this and end in anything
you
your life is
the best evidence you have
of anything
and uh the logical extrapolations that
you can make from your own personal
experience
uh and beingness
are what you should trust not
what some second-hand source says in a
book or even a person on youtube and
then you know the extrapolations that
you make from there you're going to go
into nonsense land
even for things as simple as like don't
you know the world is sphere
it's like
is that your experience
i'm not saying you should say that it's
you know
it's flat in every instance but i'm just
saying like
you know
and i'm not definitely not what people
would define as flat earther but i just
think
space is an emergent phenomenon guys
like it's not fundamental so that's my
position on it so we should just
there's no
when you're outside the space looking in
on that space it's a sphere
when you're inside of a space looking
out it's a you're gonna experience plane
and uh
so that's the reality like it's not even
an argument but if you're
either of those two perspectives where
you're like the earth is flat
people are like the earth is a sphere we
you know astronauts
that have been outside of the earth and
experienced it as a sphere like that guy
who has experienced it as a sphere
should never ever ever believe anybody
who has
uh who is saying it's just flat but he
has two perspectives one is the
perspective that this is flat
and two
the perspective that this is a sphere so
he has two
perspectives and he should believe both
but if you've only been here
then only one of those is one that you
can truly trust as you know not a sphere
but that doesn't mean you shouldn't
believe
that it is a sphere
but it
uh if you're outside it what it means is
that you shouldn't let that thought
override the thought or uh the
experience that you have had firsthand
that doesn't mean you can't believe
uh
that in
some circumstance it
it is uh congruent
and
with or it's not mutually exclusive of
your experience
firsthand but it has to in some way
eventually
be reconciled with your experience
firsthand if it's not
then it's wrong and you have to treat it
as such
so with that thank you everyone please
hit the like button please share this i
hope this made sense um if not write in
the comments below uh
what you think didn't make sense or what
you think did make sense and uh like i
said with i will not be
having the call on thursday
uh i have a date but
i will be back on tuesday and i believe
next week should not be a problem either
of having a call so we'll see depending
on how
quickly i get back maybe i'll jump on
but
uh don't bet on it
anyways with that peace guys and thank
you